{
  "reference_number": "2331",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a goal to reach net zero emissions by the second half of the century and the Climate Change Commission advises on the specific target for the Government to set later",
      "answer_index": 11,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions (including from new forest planting) and using some emissions reductions from overseas (international carbon units) that have strong environmental safeguards",
      "answer_index": 2,
      "notes": "I only favor option two because I feel that it MAY help to preserve or expand forested areas in developing nations. This MUST be\n strongly policed to ensure that it is not scammed. This could provide a win-win."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "The only acceptable alternative should be reaching carbon zero ahead of time. It should not be accepted to keep pushing the date\n\n back."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - each incoming Government should have the option to review the third budget in the sequence",
      "answer_index": 14,
      "notes": "I support this in theory, only because I realize that it might be hard to accurately consider all options so far ahead. My concern is that\n this should not become a tool that allows elections to be run on the premise of lowering targets, thereby kicking the can down the\n\n road. However, on the other side of the coin, if three lax targets were set by a lazy government, I would support a visionary\n government being able to review and set stricter targets."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Only under exceptional circumstances and only with cross party majority support."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I think that the availability of technology to enable a certain outcome needs to be considered. It may be that new tech becomes\n\navailable that allows for greater gains to be made, thereby potentially setting the goalpost higher. Certainly the economy must be\nconsidered as well. That is not to say that the government should kick the can down the road for the benefit of a few industries. It is\n\nactually to say that if some sector or part of society is having trouble keeping up, there should be assistance from government to aid\nwith transition. This might be new tech for industry or it might be training for people who lose jobs when an industry fails, or it might\n\nbe assisting the least fortunate so they do not suffer more than more fortunate people. In a perfect world, the least fortunate would\nbe trained to help implement the new technologies required in the new economy."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I would like to see the Climate Commission be an agency with teeth, that holds government to account. I do not want a Climate\nCommission that is pushed around or even dissolved by the government of the day. We cannot risk having a change of government\n\nundo all of the progress that was made by the last."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Makes decisions itself in respect of the number of units available in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 10,
      "notes": "I think the Climate Commission should take the lead and not allow lazy governments to hand out free passes."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Certainly the commission should have a wide range of expertise and it should have a very large contingent of scientists from several\ndisciplines (climate, ocean, agricultural etc.), and they should not be outnumbered by economists. Economists are important, but\n\nthey should not have the last word. I also feel that the commission should represent all political sides, providing a balance so we do\nnot have the commission stacked by a government that does not want to take real action."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I believe that a free market society will not respond fast enough due to the fact that those with a risk of stranded assets tend to try to\nslow or halt change. We need directives set out and pathways to get there. This might force those with skin in the game to help the\ntransition rather than hinder it."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Once again, the legislation must have teeth and not be something that can be pushed aside by the next government. There must be\nconsistency. We can not afford the back and forth that we have had since National pushed aside Simon Upton. We cannot have this\n\nbe a political football. We must be united. Furthermore, we need to communicate to the public that the government will need to use\ntax money to help industry and individuals transition. To some, this will sound like socialism and there may be push back. However,\n\nwe all pay taxes to be used for the greater good and they should be used to help NZ as a whole to transition. Whether that means\nhelping the dairy industry to kick coal, or if it means helping a poor west coast community to transition or poor families to retrain; then\n\nso be it!"
    }
  ]
}
